<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Andrew W. Stevens</origin>
        <origin>Guy R. Gelfenbaum</origin>
        <origin>Jonathan A. Warrick</origin>
        <origin>Ian M. Miller</origin>
        <origin>Heather M. Weiner</origin>
        <pubdate>20230522</pubdate>
        <title>Nearshore bathymetry data from the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022</title>
        <geoform>comma-delimited text</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>data release</sername>
          <issue>DOI:10.5066/P9N7N9P0</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center, Santa Cruz, California</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</onlink>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cb28d34eb496d1d1d70e</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Andrew W. Stevens</origin>
            <origin>Guy R. Gelfenbaum</origin>
            <origin>Jonathan A. Warrick</origin>
            <origin>Ian M. Miller</origin>
            <origin>Heather M. Weiner</origin>
            <pubdate>2023</pubdate>
            <title>Bathymetry, topography, and sediment grain-size data from the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022</title>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>data release</sername>
              <issue>DOI:10.5066/P9N7N9P0</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center, Santa Cruz, CA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Suggested Citation: Stevens, A.W., Gelfenbaum, G.R., Warrick, J.A., Miller, I.M., and Weiner, H.M., 2023, Bathymetry, topography, and sediment grain-size data from the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0.</othercit>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This portion of the USGS data release presents bathymetric data collected during surveys performed on the Elwha River delta, Washington in 2022 (USGS Field Activity Number 2022-638-FA). Bathymetric data were collected using personal watercraft (PWCs) and a kayak equipped with single-beam sonar systems and global navigation satellite system (GNSS) receivers.</abstract>
      <purpose>Data were obtained to assess the coastal geomorphic response following the removal of two dams on the Elwha River. These data are intended for science researchers, students, policy makers, and the general public. These data can be used with geographic information systems or other software to identify topographic and shallow-water bathymetric features.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Additional information about the field activities from which these data were derived is available online at:

https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2022-638-FA

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20220808</begdate>
          <enddate>20220811</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Ground condition at time data were collected</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-123.5907933</westbc>
        <eastbc>-123.4027499</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.1589927</northbc>
        <southbc>48.1320233</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>elevation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Data Categories for Marine Planning</themekt>
        <themekey>Bathymetry and Elevation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>bathymetry</themekey>
        <themekey>GPS measurement</themekey>
        <themekey>sea-floor characteristics</themekey>
        <themekey>marine geophysics</themekey>
        <themekey>single-beam echo sounder</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Marine Realms Information Bank (MRIB) keywords</themekt>
        <themekey>Global Positioning System (GPS) observations</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
        <themekey>USGS</themekey>
        <themekey>Coastal and Marine Hazards and Resources Program</themekey>
        <themekey>CMHRP</themekey>
        <themekey>Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</themekey>
        <themekey>PCMSC</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:6418cb28d34eb496d1d1d70e</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>Clallam County</placekey>
        <placekey>Olympic Peninsula</placekey>
        <placekey>Strait of Juan de Fuca</placekey>
        <placekey>Elwha River</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain from the U.S. Government and are freely redistributable with proper metadata and source attribution. Please recognize and acknowledge the U.S. Geological Survey as the originator(s) of the dataset and in products derived from these data. This information is not intended for navigation purposes.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>PCMSC Science Data Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2885 Mission Street</address>
          <city>Santa Cruz</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95060</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>831-427-4747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pcmsc_data@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <native>MATLAB Version: 9.8.0.1396136 (R2020a)</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>International Hydrographic Organization (IHO)</origin>
        <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
        <title>IHO standards for hydrographic surveys (5th ed.)</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Dataset is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>A series of benchmarks with known coordinates were established adjacent to the study area to provide geodetic control for the bathymetric surveys. The positions of the benchmarks were derived from a minimum of two static GNSS occupations. The equipment for the static occupations consisted of a dual frequency GNSS receiver, a fixed-height tripod, and antenna. The static observations were recorded internally in the receiver and the raw observations were processed using the National Geodetic Survey Online Positioning User Service (OPUS, https://www.ngs.noaa.gov/OPUS/). Estimated uncertainties in the horizontal position of the individual GNSS occupations were provided by OPUS and ranged between 0.006 m and 0.06 m with an average horizontal uncertainty of 0.02 m. The processed positions from each occupation were averaged to obtain the final reported position of the benchmark. All final positions of the survey vessels were determined using differential corrections from the base station receivers. Manufacturer reported accuracy for the differentially corrected horizontal positions for the GNSS rover trajectories is 0.8 cm + 0.5 ppm. Baselines from the GNSS base station were typically less than 5 km, suggesting a horizontal accuracy of survey-vessel positions to be 0.825 cm. The combined horizontal uncertainty from the base station coordinate solutions and rover trajectories is between 1.5 cm and 7 cm, with a mean horizontal uncertainty of 3 cm. Uncertainty in the horizontal positions associated with pitch and roll of the survey vessels is unknown.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Uncertainty in the final elevations is derived from the combination of uncertainty in the GNSS positioning and bathymetric sounding measurements. Manufacturer reported accuracy for the differentially corrected vertical positions for the GNSS rover trajectories is 1.5 cm + 1 ppm. Baselines from the GNSS base station were typically less than 5 km, suggesting the vertical accuracy of survey vessel positions to be 2 cm relative to the base station coordinate. Combining the uncertainty in the elevation of the base station coordinates and rover positions yields a total uncertainty in the GNSS-derived survey-vessel positions of approximately 5 cm. Additional uncertainty in the final computed elevations data is related to unmeasured variability in the speed of sound used to compute depths from bathymetric soundings and, thus, are depth-dependent. Based on analysis of all available speed of sound measurements, we estimate uncertainties in the final depth soundings to be 0.6 percent of the water depth. The total vertical uncertainty is calculated using Equation 1: sigmat=sqrt(a^2+(bxd)^2), where sigmat is the total vertical uncertainty, a is the uncertainty of the GNSS vertical position, b is the depth-dependent uncertainty factor (0.006), and d is water depth (International Hydrographic Organization, 2008). Maximum water depths surveyed on this mapping mission are approximately 18 m yielding a maximum total vertical uncertainty of 12 cm. Uncertainty in the vertical positions associated with pitch and roll of the survey vessels is unknown.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Bathymetry data were collected between August 8 and 11, 2022, using single-beam sonar systems and global navigation satellite systems (GNSS) receivers mounted on personal watercraft (PWC) and a kayak. Depths from the echosounders were computed using sound velocity profiles measured using a CTD during the survey. Positioning of the survey vessels was determined at 10 Hz using survey-grade GNSS receivers. Output from the GNSS receivers and sonar systems were combined in real time by a computer running HYPACK hydrographic survey software. Navigation information was displayed on a video monitor, allowing vessel operators to navigate along planned survey lines.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20220811</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Survey-grade positions of the vessels were achieved with a single-base station and differential post-processing. Positioning data from the GNSS receivers were post-processed using Waypoint Grafnav to apply differential corrections from a GNSS base station with known horizontal and vertical coordinates relative to the North American Datum of 1983. Orthometric elevations relative to the NAVD88 vertical datum were computed assuming a static geoid value of -20.11 m which is based on the NGS Geoid09 offset at the location of the GNSS base station. Bathymetric data were merged with post-processed positioning data and spurious soundings were removed using a custom Graphical User Interface (GUI) programmed with the computer program MATLAB. The final point data are projected in cartesian coordinates using the Washington State Plane North, meters coordinate system.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20220829</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>All available bathymetry data from the survey were compiled into a comma-delimited text file for distribution</procdesc>
        <procdate>20230306</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>1073823</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>0.0000001</latres>
        <longres>0.0000001</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum>
        <altres>0.01</altres>
        <altunits>meters</altunits>
        <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
      </altsys>
    </vertdef>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the dataset</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>datetime_utc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The date and time of data collection in Coordinated Universal Time (UTC).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>2022-Aug-08 20:07:21.289</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2022-Aug-11 19:48:11.601</rdommax>
            <attrunit>date and time in yyyy-mmm-dd HH:MM:SS.FFF format</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>longitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Longitude coordinate of data point relative to the North American Datum of 1983</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-123.5907933</rdommin>
            <rdommax>-123.4027499</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Decimal degrees</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>latitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Latitude coordinate of data point relative to the North American Datum of 1983</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>48.1320233</rdommin>
            <rdommax>48.1589927</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Decimal degrees</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>easting_m</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>East coordinate of data point relative to the North American Datum of 1983, projected in the Washington State Plane North, meters, coordinate system</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>294845.23</rdommin>
            <rdommax>308828.43</rdommax>
            <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>northing_m</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>North coordinate of data point relative to the North American Datum of 1983, projected in the Washington State Plane South, meters, coordinate system</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>129309.04</rdommin>
            <rdommax>132428.62</rdommax>
            <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ortho_ht_m</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Height in meters relative to the NAVD88 vertical datum, computed assuming a static geoid value of -20.11 m which is based on the NGS Geoid09 offset at the location of the GNSS base station</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-19.02</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.92</rdommax>
            <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The first line of the csv file is a header line.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>U.S. Geological Survey</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - Science Base</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Bathymetry data are available as a comma-delimited text file (ew22_bathy.csv), along with associated FGDC-compliant metadata.</resdesc>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>comma-delimited text</formname>
          <formvern>MATLAB Version: 9.8.0.1396136 (R2020a)</formvern>
          <formcont>comma-delimited text file</formcont>
          <filedec>No compression applied</filedec>
          <transize>78.03</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/6418cb28d34eb496d1d1d70e?name=ew22_bathy.csv</networkr>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cb28d34eb496d1d1d70e</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F72N51GC</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Data can be downloaded using the Network_Resource_Name links. The first link is a direct link to download the bathymetry data. The second link points to a landing page with all bathymetry data and metadata. The third link points to a landing page for the annual survey. The fourth link points to a landing page for the entire data release.</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20230522</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>PCMSC Science Data Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2885 Mission Street</address>
          <city>Santa Cruz</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95060</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>831-427-4747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pcmsc_data@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
