<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Andrew W. Stevens</origin>
        <origin>Guy R. Gelfenbaum</origin>
        <origin>Jonathan A. Warrick</origin>
        <origin>Ian M. Miller</origin>
        <origin>Heather M. Weiner</origin>
        <pubdate>20230522</pubdate>
        <title>Digital elevation models (DEMs) of the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022</title>
        <geoform>comma-delimited text</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>data release</sername>
          <issue>DOI:10.5066/P9N7N9P0</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center, Santa Cruz, California</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</onlink>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/64077140d34e76f5f75e388f</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Andrew W. Stevens</origin>
            <origin>Guy R. Gelfenbaum</origin>
            <origin>Jonathan A. Warrick</origin>
            <origin>Ian M. Miller</origin>
            <origin>Heather M. Weiner</origin>
            <pubdate>2023</pubdate>
            <title>Bathymetry, topography, and sediment grain-size data from the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022</title>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>data release</sername>
              <issue>DOI:10.5066/P9N7N9P0</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center, Santa Cruz, CA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Suggested Citation: Stevens, A.W., Gelfenbaum, G.R., Warrick, J.A., Miller, I.M., and Weiner, H.M., 2023, Bathymetry, topography, and sediment grain-size data from the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0.</othercit>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This portion of the USGS data release presents digital elevation models (DEMs) derived from bathymetric and topographic surveys conducted on the Elwha River delta in August 2022 (USGS Field Activity Number 2022-638-FA). Nearshore bathymetry data were collected using two personal watercraft (PWCs) and a kayak equipped with single-beam echosounders and survey-grade global navigation satellite systems (GNSS) receivers. Topographic data were collected on foot with survey-grade GNSS receivers mounted on backpacks. Positions of the survey platforms were referenced to a GNSS base station placed on a benchmark with known horizontal and vertical coordinates relative to the North American Datum of 1983 (CORS96 realization) and North American Vertical Datum of 1988 based on NGS Geoid09 vertical offsets. The final data were projected in Cartesian coordinates using the Washington State Plane North (meters) coordinate system. A total of 1,285,634 individual elevation points were collected within the survey area between August 8 and August 11, 2022. DEM surfaces were produced from all available elevation data using linear interpolation. Two separate DEMs were constructed. A DEM was produced that covered the entire survey area (approximately 482 ha) with 5-m horizontal resolution. A second DEM with 1-m resolution was produced that covered the river mouth and adjacent areas (approximately 209 ha). The DEMs were created by interpolating between measurements as much as 50 meters apart. For this reason, we cannot evaluate the accuracy of each point in the DEM, only the measurements it is based on. The estimated vertical uncertainties of the bathymetric and topographic measurements are 12 and 5 cm, respectively. Digital data files for each DEM are provided in ESRI ARC ASCII (*.asc) format.</abstract>
      <purpose>Data were obtained to assess the coastal geomorphic response following the removal of two dams on the Elwha River. These data are intended for science researchers, students, policy makers, and the general public. These data can be used with geographic information systems or other software to identify topographic and shallow-water bathymetric features.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Additional information about the field activities from which these data were derived is available online at:

https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2022-638-FA

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.
Although this Federal Geographic Data Committee-compliant metadata file is intended to document the data set in nonproprietary form, as well as in Esri format, this metadata file may include some Esri-specific terminology.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20220811</begdate>
          <enddate>20220811</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Ground condition at time data were collected</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-123.591573</westbc>
        <eastbc>-123.521062</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.159542</northbc>
        <southbc>48.135070</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>elevation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Data Categories for Marine Planning</themekt>
        <themekey>Bathymetry and Elevation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>bathymetry</themekey>
        <themekey>bathymetry measurement</themekey>
        <themekey>topography</themekey>
        <themekey>GPS measurement</themekey>
        <themekey>digital elevation models</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Marine Realms Information Bank (MRIB) keywords</themekt>
        <themekey>single-beam echo sounder</themekey>
        <themekey>topographic mapping</themekey>
        <themekey>Global Positioning System (GPS) observations</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
        <themekey>USGS</themekey>
        <themekey>Coastal and Marine Hazards and Resources Program</themekey>
        <themekey>CMHRP</themekey>
        <themekey>Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</themekey>
        <themekey>PCMSC</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>Clallam County</placekey>
        <placekey>Olympic Peninsula</placekey>
        <placekey>Strait of Juan de Fuca</placekey>
        <placekey>Elwha River</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain from the U.S. Government and are freely redistributable with proper metadata and source attribution. Please recognize and acknowledge the U.S. Geological Survey as the originator(s) of the dataset and in products derived from these data. This information is not intended for navigation purposes.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>PCMSC Science Data Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2885 Mission Street</address>
          <city>Santa Cruz</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95060</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>831-427-4747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pcmsc_data@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708?name=ew22_dem_5m.png&amp;allowOpen=true</browsen>
      <browsed>image map showing 5-m resolution digital elevation model (DEM) of Elwha River delta, color-coded to show elevation</browsed>
      <browset>PNG</browset>
    </browse>
    <browse>
      <browsen>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708?name=ew22_dem_1m.png&amp;allowOpen=true</browsen>
      <browsed>image map showing 1-m resolution digital elevation model (DEM) of Elwha River mouth, color-coded to show elevation</browsed>
      <browset>PNG</browset>
    </browse>
    <native>MATLAB Version 9.8.0.1396136 (R2020a)</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>International Hydrographic Organization (IHO)</origin>
        <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
        <title>IHO standards for hydrographic surveys (5th ed.)</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Dataset is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Digital elevation models (DEMs) are created by interpolating between elevation measurements as much as 50 meters apart, for this reason we cannot evaluate the accuracy of each point in a DEM, only the original data from which it is generated. The horizontal accuracy of the individual points was assessed based on the combined uncertainty of GNSS base stations and kinematic (rover) data points. Manufacturer-reported accuracy for the differentially corrected horizontal positions for the Trimble R7, R8 and R10 receivers used to collect the topographic and bathymetric measurements is 0.8 cm + 0.5 ppm. Baselines from the GNSS base station were typically less than 5 km, suggesting a horizontal accuracy of survey-vessel positions to be 0.825 cm relative to the base station. The combined horizontal uncertainty from the base station coordinate solutions and rover trajectories is between 1.5 cm and 7 cm, with a mean horizontal uncertainty of 3 cm. Uncertainty in the horizontal positions associated with pitch and roll of the survey vessels and variable surveyor posture during the backpack surveys is unknown.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Digital elevation models (DEMs) are created by interpolating between elevation measurements as much as 50 meters apart, for this reason we cannot evaluate the accuracy of each point in a DEM, only the original data from which it is generated. An estimated vertical accuracy of 5 cm for the topographic GNSS backpack survey platforms was estimated by combining uncertainty in the base station coordinates and the manufacturer reported vertical accuracy of 1.5 cm + 1 ppm for differential corrected kinematic data. Additional uncertainty in the final computed elevations in the bathymetry data is related to unmeasured variability in the speed of sound used to compute depths from bathymetric soundings and, thus, are depth dependent. Based on analysis of all available sound velocity casts, we estimate the uncertainty in the final elevations to be 0.6 percent of water depth. The total vertical uncertainty is calculated using the standard equation sigmat=v(a^2+(b×d)^2), where sigmat is the total vertical uncertainty, a is the uncertainty of the GNSS vertical position, b is the depth-dependent uncertainty factor (0.006), and d is water depth (International Hydrographic Organization, 2008). Maximum water depths surveyed by the personal watercraft are approximately 18 m, yielding a maximum total vertical uncertainty of 12 cm.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Andrew W. Stevens</origin>
            <origin>Guy R. Gelfenbaum</origin>
            <origin>Jonathan A. Warrick</origin>
            <origin>Ian M. Miller</origin>
            <origin>Heather M. Weiner</origin>
            <pubdate>2023</pubdate>
            <title>Nearshore bathymetry data from the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022</title>
            <geoform>comma-delimited text</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>online</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cb28d34eb496d1d1d70e</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital dataset</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20220808</begdate>
              <enddate>20220811</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition at time data were collected</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>bathy data</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Bathymetry data were combined with topography data, and then interpolated into a gridded surface</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Andrew W. Stevens</origin>
            <origin>Guy R. Gelfenbaum</origin>
            <origin>Jonathan A. Warrick</origin>
            <origin>Ian M. Miller</origin>
            <origin>Heather M. Weiner</origin>
            <pubdate>2023</pubdate>
            <title>Topography data from the Elwha River delta, Washington, August 2022</title>
            <geoform>comma-delimited text</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>online</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cb68d34eb496d1d1d715</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital dataset</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20220809</begdate>
              <enddate>20220811</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition at time data were collected</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>topo data</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Topography data were combined with bathymetry data, and then interpolated into a gridded surface</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Quality control was applied to raw topography and bathymetry data. Comparisons were performed to ensure internal consistency between the survey platforms. DEMs were produced by linear interpolation of all available elevation point data with the computer program MATLAB. Data were exported in ESRI ARC ascii grid format for distribution.</procdesc>
        <srcused>bathy data</srcused>
        <srcused>topo data</srcused>
        <procdate>20230306</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>State Plane Coordinate System 1983</gridsysn>
          <spcs>
            <spcszone>4601</spcszone>
            <lambertc>
              <stdparll>47.5</stdparll>
              <stdparll>48.73333333333333</stdparll>
              <longcm>-120.8333333333333</longcm>
              <latprjo>47.0</latprjo>
              <feast>500000.0</feast>
              <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
            </lambertc>
          </spcs>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plance>row and column</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.001</absres>
            <ordres>0.001</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum>
        <altres>0.01</altres>
        <altunits>meters</altunits>
        <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
      </altsys>
    </vertdef>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Elevation</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Height in meters relative to the NAVD88 vertical datum, computed assuming a static geoid value of -20.11 m which is based on the NGS Geoid09 offset at the location of the GNSS base station. Elevation range given here is for the 5-m resolution overall DEM.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-18.72</rdommin>
            <rdommax>5.08</rdommax>
            <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - Science Base</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>1-m and 5-m resolution DEM grids are available in Esri ARC/INFO ASCII GRID format (.asc), along with low-resolution browse graphics of each DEM in png format and associated FGDC-compliant metadata.</resdesc>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcInfo GRID format</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 10.1</formvern>
          <formspec>Esri ARC/INFO ASCII GRID</formspec>
          <formcont>Esri ARC ASCII raster containing 1-m resolution digital elevation model of the Elwha River mouth</formcont>
          <filedec>none</filedec>
          <transize>14.27</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708/?name=ew22_dem_1m.asc</networkr>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F72N51GC</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Data can be downloaded using the Network_Resource_Name links. The first link is a direct link to download the 1-m resolution DEM data. The second link points to a landing page with all DEM data and metadata. The third link points to the landing page for the August 2022 data release. The fourth link points to a landing page for all of the Elwha annual surveys.</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcInfo GRID format</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 10.1</formvern>
          <formspec>Esri ARC/INFO ASCII GRID</formspec>
          <formcont>Esri ASCII raster file containing 5-m resolution digital elevation model of the Elwha River delta</formcont>
          <filedec>none</filedec>
          <transize>4.00</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708/?name=ew22_dem_5m.asc</networkr>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F72N51GC</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Data can be downloaded using the Network_Resource_Name links. The first link is a direct link to download the 5-m resolution DEM data. The second link points to a landing page with all DEM data and metadata. The third link points to the landing page for the August 2022 data release. The fourth link points to a landing page for all of the Elwha annual surveys.</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>png</formname>
          <formvern>MATLAB Version 9.8.0.1396136 (R2020a)</formvern>
          <formspec>PNG Image</formspec>
          <formcont>PNG image showing 1-m resolution digital elevation model of the Elwha River mouth</formcont>
          <filedec>none</filedec>
          <transize>1.76</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708/?name=ew22_dem_1m.png</networkr>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F72N51GC</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Data can be downloaded using the Network_Resource_Name links. The first link is a direct link to download the DEM data. The second link points to a landing page with all DEM data and metadata. The third link points to a landing page for the August 2022 data release. The fourth link points to a landing page for the entire data release.</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>png</formname>
          <formvern>MATLAB Version 9.8.0.1396136 (R2020a)</formvern>
          <formspec>PNG Image</formspec>
          <formcont>PNG image showing 5-m resolution digital elevation model of the Elwha River delta</formcont>
          <filedec>none</filedec>
          <transize>0.91</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708/?name=ew22_dem_5m.png</networkr>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/6418cab4d34eb496d1d1d708</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9N7N9P0</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F72N51GC</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Data can be downloaded using the Network_Resource_Name links. The first link is a direct link to download the bathymetry data. The second link points to a landing page with all bathymetry data and metadata. The third link points to a landing page for the annual survey. The fourth link points to a landing page for the entire data release.</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20230522</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Pacific Coastal and Marine Science Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>PCMSC Science Data Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2885 Mission Street</address>
          <city>Santa Cruz</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95060</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>831-427-4747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pcmsc_data@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
